If you're at all like me,
إذا كنتم جميعا مثلي
this is what you do with the sunny summer weekends in San Francisco:
هذا ما ستفعلونه في عطلة نهاية أسبوع مشمسة في سان فرانسيسكو
you build experimental kite-powered hydrofoils
تجربون بناء قوارب ذات زعانف ورقية
capable of more than 30 knots.
قادرة على تحمل أكثر من 30 عقدة
And you realize that there is incredible power in the wind,
,وستدركون أن للريح قوة لا تصدق
and it can do amazing things.
قادرة على القيام بأشياء مذهلة
And one day, a vessel not unlike this
و في يوم ما، يمكن أن نرى سفينة لا تختلف كثيرا عن هذه
will probably break the world speed record.
تتمكن من تحطيم الرقم القياسي العالمي للسرعة
But kites aren't just toys like this.
الطائرات الورقية ليست مجرد العاب مثل هذه
Kites: I'm going to give you a brief history,
,سأقدم لمحة تاريخية عن الطائرات الورقية
and tell you about the magnificent future
وسأخبركم عن المستقبل الرائع
of every child's favorite plaything.
،للعبة المفضلة لكل طفل
So, kites are more than a thousand years old,
،إذن، يفوق عمر الطائرات الورقية الألف سنة
and the Chinese used them for military applications,
،و قد استخدمها الصينيون في تطبيقات عسكرية
and even for lifting men.
وحتى في رفع رجل إلى الأعلى
So they knew at that stage they could carry large weights.
إذن كانوا يعلمون في تلك المرحلة أنها يمكن أن تحمل أوزانا كبيرة
I'm not sure why there is a hole in this particular man.
لست متأكدا من سبب وجود ثقب في جسم هذا الرجل الاستثنائي
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
In 1827, a fellow called George Pocock
في 1827 ، زميل يدعى جورج بوكوك
actually pioneered the use of kites for towing buggies
قام بدور رائد في استخدام الطائرات الورقية لسحب العربات
in races against horse carriages across the English countryside.
في السباقات بدل السحب باستعمال الخيل في الريف الانجليزي
Then of course, at the dawn of aviation,
،بعد ذلك ، في فجر الطيران بالطبع
all of the great inventors of the time --
-- جميع عظماء المخترعين في ذلك الوقت
like Hargreaves, like Langley,
،مثل هارجريفز ، مثل لانغلي
even Alexander Graham Bell, inventor of the telephone, who was flying this kite --
أو حتى الكسندر غراهام بيل،مخترع الهاتف،ممن أطلقوا طائرات ورقية
were doing so in the pursuit of aviation.
كانوا يفعلون ذلك في إطار السعي إلى الطيران
Then these two fellows came along,
،ثم جاء هذين الزميلين
and they were flying kites to develop the control systems
وكانوا يطلقون طائرة ورقية لتطوير أنظمة المراقبة
that would ultimately enable powered human flight.
التي من شأنها في نهاية المطاف أن تسمح برحلة مؤهولة
So this is of course Orville and Wilbur Wright,
و هؤلاء بالطبع هم أورفيل ويلبر رايت
and the Wright Flyer.
ورايت فلاير
And their experiments with kites led to this
وتجاربهم على الطائرات الورقية أدت إلى هذه
momentous occasion, where we powered up and took off for the
المناسبة العظيمة ، حيث تم تطويرها وغادرت الأرض
first-ever 12-second human flight.
لأول اثنا عشر ثانية من الطيران المأهول
And that was fantastic for the future of commercial aviation.
وكان هذا أمرا رائعا لمستقبل الطيران التجاري
But unfortunately, it relegated kites once again to be considered children's toys.
ولكن للأسف، تم التخلي من جديد عن الطائرات الورقية و اعتبرت مجرد ألعاب للأطفال
That was until the 1970s, where we had the last energy crisis.
واستمر الامر هكذا حتى سنة 1970،حيث وقعت أزمة الطاقة الأخيرة
And a fabulous man called Miles Loyd
قام شخص رائع يدعى مايلز لويد
who lives on the outskirts of San Francisco,
يعيش على مشارف مدينة سان فرانسيسكو
wrote this seminal paper that was completely ignored
،قام بكتابة تلك الوثيقة الهامة و التي لم تلقى الا تجاهلا تاما
in the Journal of Energy
،"في يومية "انرجي
about how to use basically an airplane on a piece of string
حول كيفية استخدام طائرة
to generate enormous amounts of electricity.
لتوليد كميات هائلة من الكهرباء
The real key observation he made is that
أهم الملاحظات التي استنتجها هي أن
a free-flying wing can sweep through more sky and generate more power
الطيران بجناح حر يمكّن من مسح أكبر للسماء وتوليد كمية طاقةأكبر
in a unit of time than a fixed-wing turbine.
في وحدة من الزمان و ذلك مقارنة بطائرة توربينية ثابتة الجناح
So turbines grew. And they can now span up to three hundred feet at the hub height,
،تم تطوير التوربينات ويمكنها الآن الوصل إلى ارتفاع ثلاث مئة قدم
but they can't really go a lot higher,
،ولكنها لا تستطيع أن تصل إلى ارتفاع أعلى
and more height is where the more wind is, and more power --
--و حيث يكون الارتفاع أكبر تكون الرياح أكثر وأشدّ قوّة
as much as twice as much.
بنسبة الضّعف
So cut to now. We still have an energy crisis,
،الى يومنا هذا لا تزال لدينا أزمة طاقة
and now we have a climate crisis as well. You know,
،والآن لدينا أزمة المناخ أيضا كما تعلمون
so humans generate about 12 trillion watts,
،البشر يولدون نحو 12 تريليون واط
or 12 terawatts, from fossil fuels.
أو 12 تيراواط، من الوقود الأحفوري
And Al Gore has spoken to why we need to hit one of these targets,
،و آل غور بيّن لماذا نحن بحاجة لنصل إلى واحد من هذه الأهداف
and in reality what that means is in the next 30 to 40 years,
،وما يعنيه هذا في الواقع هو أنه و في غضون 30 أو 40 سنة
we have to make 10 trillion watts or more of new clean energy somehow.
علينا انتاج 10 ترليون واط أو أكثر من الطاقة النظيفة والجديدة
Wind is the second-largest renewable resource after solar:
: الرياح هي ثاني أكبر مورد متجدد بعد الشمس
3600 terawatts, more than enough to supply humanity 200 times over.
نحو 3600 تيراواط,أي اكثر 200 مرة مما تستحقه البشريّ
The majority of it is in the higher altitudes, above 300 feet,
،معظم ذلك متوفر على ارتفاعات أعلى ، تتجاوز 300 قدم
where we don't have a technology as yet to get there.
،حيث لا نملك بعد التكنولوجيا للوصول إلى هناك
So this is the dawn of the new age of kites.
،إذا هذا يمثّل فجر عصر جديد للطائرات الورقية
This is our test site on Maui, flying across the sky.
،هذا موقعنا للتجارب في " ماوي "، حيث تحلق عبر السماء
I'm now going to show you
سأريكم الآن
the first autonomous generation of power
أول توليد تلقائي الطاقة
by every child's favorite plaything.
،باستعمال اللعبة المفضلة لكل طفل
As you can tell, you need to be a robot to fly this thing for thousands of hours.
يمكن القول أن علينا استعمال روبوت ليطير هذا الشيء لآلاف الساعات
It makes you a little nauseous.
سيصيبك هذا بالغثيان قليلا
And here we're actually generating about 10 kilowatts --
-- وهنا نحن في الواقع نولد نحو 10 كيلو وات
so, enough to power probably five United States households --
-- وذلك ، تقريبا يكفي لإمداد خمس منازل في الولايات المتحدة
with a kite not much larger than this piano.
و ذلك باستعمال طائرة ورقية لا يتجاوز حجمها حجم هذا البيانو
And the real significant thing here
والأمر المهم هنا
is we're developing the control systems,
،هو أننا بصدد تطوير نظم المراقبة
as did the Wright brothers, that would enable sustained, long-duration flight.
مثلما فعل الأخوان رايت ، و هذا من شأنه أن يمكن من طيران متواصل و لمدة طويلة
And it doesn't hurt to do it in a location like this either.
،وأن القيام بهذا في مثل ذلك المكان لن يتسبب في أضرار
So this is the equivalent for a kite flier of peeing in the snow --
،فذلك يعادل سقوط الطائرة الورقية في الثلج
that's tracing your name in the sky.
وهذا يرسم اسمك في السماء
And this is where we're actually going.
وهذا هو المكان الذي نرتاده حاليا
So we're beyond the 12-second steps.
"لذلك نحن تجاوزنا خطوات ال"12 ثانية
And we're working towards megawatt-scale machines
ونحن نعمل من أجل آلات تنتج على مستوى الميغاوات
that fly at 2000 feet and generate tons of clean electricity.
وهي تحلق على علو 2000 قدم وتولد أطنانا من الكهرباء النظيفة
So you ask, how big are those machines?
لذلك نسأل ، كم يبلغ حجم هذه الآلات الكبيرة؟
Well, this paper plane would be maybe a -- oop!
حسنا ، فإن هذه الطائرة الورقية ربما ستكون --اوب
That would be enough to power your cell phone.
ستكون كافية لتشغيل هاتفك المحمول
Your Cessna would be 230 killowatts.
سيسنا خاصتك سوف تستحق230 كيلوات
If you'd loan me your Gulfstream, I'll rip its wings off and generate you a megawatt.
إذا أقرضتني "الجلفستريم" الخاصة بك ،سأشق أجنحتهاوأولد لك ميجاوات
If you give me a 747, I'll make six megawatts,
إذا أعطيت ال747 ,سأولد لك ستة ميجاوات
which is more than the largest wind turbines today.
وهو ما يفوق ما تنتجه أكبر توربينات تعمل بالرياح في أيامنا هذه
And the Spruce Goose would be a 15-megawatt wing.
و "السبروس غوس" سينتج 15 ميجاوات للجناح
So that is audacious, you say. I agree.
هذا أمر جريء ، تقول وأنا أوافقك الرأي
But audacious is what has happened many times before in history.
ولكن أمور جريئة كثيرة حدثت عدة مرات من قبل في التاريخ
This is a refrigerator factory,
هذا مصنع ثلاجات
churning out airplanes for World War II.
كان يمول الطائرات خلال الحرب العالمية الثانية
Prior to World War II, they were making 1000 planes a year.
قبل الحرب العالمية الثانية ، كانوا يصنعون 1000 طائرة كل سنة
By 1945, they were making 100,000.
مع حلول العام 1945 ، كانوا يصنعون 100،000
With this factory and 100,000 planes a year,
،مع هذا المصنع و100،000 طائرة سنويا
we could make all of America's electricity in about 10 years.
فإنه بإمكاننا أن نوفر الكهرباء للولايات المتحدة لنحو 10 أعوام
So really this is a story about the audacious plans of young people
فهذا يمثل فعلا ، قصة لمخطط جريء لمجموعة من الشباب
with these dreams. There are many of us.
مع هذه الأحلام هناك الكثير منا
I am lucky enough to work with 30 of them.
وأنا محظوظ للعمل مع 30 منهم
And I think we need to support all of the dreams
وأعتقد أنه علينا دعم كل أحلام
of the kids out there doing these crazy things.
هؤلاء الأطفال هناك لتحقيق هذه الأشياء المجنونة
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)